A Finding Aid to the Henry Bacon Papers, 1849-1931, in the Archives of American Art aaa.bacohenr
Archives of American Art
Henry Bacon papers
1849-1931
aaa.bacohenr
Archives of American Art
1.9 Linear feet
The papers of painter and writer Henry Bacon date from 1849-1931 and measure 1.9 linear feet. The collection documents Bacon's career and travels through France and Egypt. Included are biographical materials, correspondence, writings by Bacon and others, scattered business records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, eight sketchbooks and additional sketches.
Bacon, Henry, 1839-1912
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1864-circa 1930 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1849-1931 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1875-circa 1912 (Box 1-2, 5; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business and Financial records, 1864-1871 (Box 2; 2 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1882-1931 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1866-1923 (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1862-circa 1930 (Box 3-5; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1864-1912 (Box 4-5; 0.4 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Painter and writer, Henry Bacon (1839-1912) spent much of his career and life in France and Egypt. He is best known for his watercolor depictions of Egyptian desert scenes.
Henry Bacon was born in Haverhill, Massachusetts in 1839. During the Civil War, ee enlisted in the Union Army and served as corporal in Company D, 4th Battalion of Rifles of the 13th Massachusetts Regiment. Also during the war, he worked as a field artist for Leslie's Weekly. He suffered an injury at the Second Battle of Bull Run and was discharged in 1864. That same year, he married Lizzie Lord and moved to France. The couple settled in Paris where Bacon studied at the École des Beaux-Arts under Alexandre Cabanel. He spent many summers in Étretat, France--a subject he painted and wrote about in his book Étretat: Hamlet of the Setting Sun.
After the death of Lizzie Lord, Bacon married Louisa Lee Andrews. In the 1890s, Henry and Louisa spent their time split between London and Egypt. It was during this time that Bacon produced his many watercolor scenes of the desert, the Nile River, and of the Egyptian people. Henry Bacon died in Cairo in 1912.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The bulk of this collection was digitized in 2013 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1987 by Nancy N. Brecht, the grandniece of Henry Bacon and granddaughter of Bacon's brother, Earle.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and writer Henry Bacon date from 1849-1931 and measure 1.9 linear feet. The collection documents Bacon's career and travels through France and Egypt. Included are biographical materials, correspondence, writings by Bacon and others, scattered business records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, eight sketchbooks and additional sketches.
Scattered biographical materials include an address book, a photo identification card, genealogical material, and autobiographical notes and resumes. The bulk of correspondence is in French written by French artists included in Bacon's book Parisian Art and Artists, including Beaumont, E. Berne-Bellecourt, Vincent Chevillard, Luigi Chialiva, Georges Clairin, Edmond Dupain, Carolus Duran, Antonio Gonzalez, Ferdinand Heilbuth, Madeleine Lemaire, Luc Oliver Merson, and Leon Olivie. Also found is correspondence between Louisa Lee Bacon with museums and institutions concerning her husband's art.
Writings and notes contain short stories, personal accounts, and poems by Henry Bacon, as well as a biographical work on Bacon by Louisa Bacon, and unsigned poems in French. Manuscripts of Bacon's books are not found.
Scattered personal business records include a sales record notebook, an expense journal, and a lease. Printed materials consist primarily of clippings, a few exhibition catalogs, a copy of Bacon's book Étretat: Hamlet of the Setting Sun, and printed images of works of art. Two scrapbooks document Bacon's career as an artist through clippings, photos, exhibition catalogs, and announcements.
Photographs include portraits and snapshots of Bacon and his wife, travel photos used as reference, and photos of works of art. Artwork by Bacon includes eight sketchbooks, watercolor sketches, and pen and ink sketches.
Separated Materials note
Also found in the Archives are three sketchbooks lent by Nancy C. Brecht for microfilming on reels 4040-4041. The scrapbooks are not described in the container listing of this finding aid but are available for viewing in Archives of American Art offices and via interlibrary loan.
Bacon, Lee Andrews, 1861-; Beaumont; Berne-Bellecourt, E.; Carolus-Duran, 1837 or 8-1917; Chevillard, Vincent; Chialiva, Luigi, 1841-1914; Clairin, Georges, 1843-1919; Dupain, Edmond-Louis, 1847-1933; Gonzales, Antonio; Heilbuth, Ferdinand; Lemaire, Madeleine-Jeanne Coll, 1845-1928; Merson, Luc Olivier, 1846-1920; Olivie, Leon; Artists--France--Paris; Authors--France--Paris; Egypt--Description and travel; Landscape painters; Painters--United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1864-circa 1930; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found is an address book, a declaration for American artists signed by Louisa Lee and Henry Bacon, geneological material of the Munro-Bacon family, an identification card with Bacon's photo for the 1889 exposition in Paris, a list of founding members of the Société des Elèves de l'Atelier Cabanel, an engraved menu for a dinner held at the Palais d'Abdine in Cairo, a form granted by the Louvre giving Bacon permission to copy a painting, and autobiographical notes and resumes.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Address Book, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Declaration of American Artists, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Geneology, after 1922 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Identification Card, Exposition Universelle, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership List, Société des Elèves de l'Atelier Cabanel, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Menu, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Permission Form, Musée du Louvre, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resumes and Autobiographical Notes, circa 1910-circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1849-1931; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  The bulk of this series consists of scattered letters written in French by artists featured in a book by Bacon and from Bacon's fellow students of Alexandre Cabanel. Researchers should note that some of the signatures are illegible. A letter from Henri de Courmont is an acceptance letter to the École des Beaux-Arts. A letter from Charles Insley Pardee grants honorary membership to the Lotus Club in New York City. Also found is a letter from Henry Bacon Sr., and two letters from American school children writing to Bacon to request snapshots of Egypt. There is correspondence between Louisa Lee Bacon Eldrich to museums and institutions concerning her husband's works of art and donations. A letter written in French to Mr. Romuu from Mr. Henry Vigrand (?) is likely a letter of introduction from the French government to that of Andorra for Henry Bacon.
  Artist letters in this series from Bacon's book Parisian Art and Artists include: Beaumont, E. Berne-Bellecourt, Vincent Chevillard, Luigi Chialiva, Georges Clairin, Edmond Dupain, Carolus Duran, Antonio Gonzalez, Ferdinand Heilbuth, Madeleine Lemaire, Luc Oliver Merson, and Leon Olivie. Letters from the students of Alexandre Cabanel include Bartholdi, Edmond Borchard, Pierre Cabanel, Horace de Callias, Benjamin Constant, Fernand Cormon, Edmond Dupain,M.H. Gaudefroy, Jules Girardet, Charles Gosselin, E. Hamm, G. Haquette, and E. Renar.
  - Bacon, Henry Sr., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bartholdi, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beaumont, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berne-Bellecour, Etienne Prosper, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boone, J. Allen, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Borchard, Edmond, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cabanel, Pierre, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Callias, Horace de, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carolus-Duran, Emile-August, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chevilliard, Vincent, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chialivas, Luigi, circa 1880; 1879 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clairin, Georges (?), 1879 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Constant, Benjamin, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Courmont, Henri de, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cormon, Ferdinand, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dupain, Edmond-Louis, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gaudefroy, M. H., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Girardet, Jules, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gonzalez, Antonio (?), 1879 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gosselin, Charles, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Haquette, Georges Jean Marie, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hamm, E., circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Heilbuth, Ferdinand, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - LeMarie, Madeline, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Merson, Luc Oliver, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Olivie, Leon, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Pardee, Charles Insley, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Renard, E., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Survillez, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Wadleigh, Levi C., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Illegible, French Artists, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Illegible, French Artists, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Wedding Invitation, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Louisa Lee Bacon Eldrich Correspondence, 1914-1931 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Mr. Henry Vigrand (?) to Mr. Romuu, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Writings and Notes, 1875-circa 1912; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2, 5
  Found are short stories and personal accounts concerning art, museums, and travel. There is a written account of a meeting with Cecil Rhodes shortly before his death entitled "Meeting with Cecil Rhodes," and "The Artist in Pre-Cromo Days," an account of Bacon's experiences as an art student, his first visit to Ecouen, and encounters with Edouard Frère, J.F. Millet, and Corot. There is a twenty-two page biographical work by Louisa Lee Bacon about her husband. Also found are poems and a poetry notebook by Bacon and scattered poems written in French by unknown authors.
  - "A Wonderfull [sic] Voyage for 4 Sons", 1894 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Roman Models", 1896 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "The Artist in Pre-Cromo Days", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "The Black Sheep of Doxviller", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "In Venice", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, Folder 1
  - "Je Ne Sais Pas", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Monsieur, le Dauphin de France", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "Palace of the Louvre", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "Papa was Coming Home!", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Siena", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "To Miss C", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Widow Jones' Man", circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Untitled Work, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Pages 2-5 are missing
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F1
  - "Great Temple of Abou Simnel: Nubia", circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Meeting with Cecil Rhodes", circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Poetry Notebook, 1875-1891 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Poems, 1875-1897 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes and Fragments, circa 1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Henry Bacon- Figure and Landscape Painter, 1839-1912," by Lee Bacon, circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - French Poetry, by Unknown, circa 1880 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Writings, circa 1880 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Material scanned with Box 1, F48
- Personal Business and Financial Records, 1864-1871; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 2
  Found is a notebook documenting the sale of Bacon's paintings from 1864-1867, an expense journal detailing expenses from a European trip in 1911, and a French document concerning Bacon's occupation of an apartment.
  - Lease or Rental Agreement, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sales Record Notebook, 1864-1867 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Expense Journal, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, 1882-1931; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2
  Found are clippings, exhibition catalogs, a copy of Étretat: Hamlet of the Setting Sun by Bacon, reproductions of works of art, and a copy of The Artists Guild journal. One exhibition catalog from 1931 is a handmade mock-up created by Louisa Lee Bacon Eldrich with both typed and handwritten names of works. Some materials are in French.
  - Clippings, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, circa 1880-circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalog, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Catalog, circa 1896 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1925-1931 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, 1882; circa 1890 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Etretat: Hamlet of the Setting Sun, by Henry Bacon (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Artists Guild, Journal, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Scrapbooks, 1866-1923; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3
  Found are two scrapbooks which relate to Henry Bacon's career as an artist. One scrapbook dates from 1866-1882 and contains mostly clippings, however one photograph is included. A second scrapbook dates from 1912-1923 and was created by Louisa Lee Bacon. It contains clippings, exhibition catalogs, notices, photographs, and a poem. Many of the clippings are in French.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1866-1882 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1912-1923 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1862-circa 1930; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3-5
  Found are portraits of the artist, snapshots, photos of works of art, and reference photos. Portraits are of Bacon, his wife Louisa Lee Bacon, and of Marie Therese de Bourbon. Portraits of Bacon are mostly in his later years, however there is a daguerreotype of the artist in his Civil War uniform. Snapshots are of the couple during their travels through France, Egypt, and Italy some of which depict Bacon painting outside in France. There are travel photos of Egypt and England used by Bacon as reference for his art.
  - Henry Bacon, Portrait in Civil War Uniform, circa 1862 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Henry Bacon, Portraits, circa 1890-1910 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Henry Bacon, Painting Outside, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Henry Bacon, in Paris, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Henry and Louisa Lee Bacon, in Venice, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Henry and Louisa Lee Bacon, in Egypt, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Louisa Lee Bacon, Portrait, circa 1870 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Grave Monument, after 1912 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Marie Therese de Boubon, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Travel and Reference Photos, Egypt, circa 1890-1900 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F2
  - Travel and Reference Photos, England, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Travel and Reference Photos, Unknown, circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Works of Art, circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Photographs, circa 1890-1900 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Material scanned with Box 3, F14
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1864-1912; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Box 4-5
  This series consists of eight sketchbooks, pen and ink illustrations, and watercolor sketches. The majority of the works depict scenes of Bacon's travels through France and Egypy and include figures in costume, desert landscapes, and seascapes. Also found are two sketches of Bacon, one by J. Carroll Beckwith and one unsigned.
  - Sketchbook, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Alcase-Lorraine and Bouxwiller, France
  - Sketchbook, 1884-1887 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Ship scenes
  - Sketchbook, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Corsica
  - Sketchbook, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Andorra
  - Sketchbook, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Egypt, Athens, and Venice
  - Sketchbook, circa 1880 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Venice
  - Sketchbook, circa 1881 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Shipboard Scenes
  - Sketchbook, circa 1888 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Possibly Étretat, France; oversized material housed in Box 5, F3
  - Drawings and Watercolors, circa 1870-circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Possibly illustrations for a book
  - Watercolor Sketches, 1891-1912 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Pencil Sketch, circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sketches of Henry Bacon by J. Carroll Bechwith and Unknown, 1864; 1874 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Watercolor Sketches, circa 1900; 1904-1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Material scanned with Box 4, F11